Speaker 1: You're just staring at the moon and smiling You're so absorbed in searching for something to gently touch Your eyes are so painful,
Shinji: He was still an angel! He was still one of the enemy!
Shinji: He wasn't! He wasn't! He wasn't!
Rei: Even though he was as human as me?
Shinji: No! He was an angel!
Rei: Is that why you killed him?
Shinji: Yes! Otherwise we'd all die! We'd have all been destroyed!
Rei: So that's why you killed him?
Shinji: I didn't want to kill him! I didn't have a choice!
Shinji: Help me! Please, just help me!
Shinji: For God's sake, help me!
Shinji: Somebody please help me!
Shinji: Is anyone listening? Somebody please help me!
Shinji: He was much better than I am.
Shinji: Karu should have survived.
Shinji: Not me.
Misato: No. The one who deserves to survive is the one who has the will to make it happen.
Misato: He wished for death.
Misato: He ignored his will to survive and chose to die for a false hope.
Misato: Survival is not a mistake, Shinji.
Shinji: Are you sure?
Shinji: Are you sure it was right?
Shinji: I don't understand.
Shinji: What can I do?
Shinji: What am I supposed to do?
Shinji: What was that?
Shinji: I fear myself?
Shinji: I fear being hated?
Shinji: But by whom?
Shinji: Who is it? It's my...
Shinji: Father.
Shinji: My father abandoned me. He hates me!
Shinji: If others hate me, what will I do?
Shinji: What will I do?
Shinji: Where am I?
Shinji: Where am I supposed to go?
Shinji: I can't see anything.
Shinji: I don't understand what I feel.
Shinji: Misato? Misato!
Shinji: Hey! Where are you, Misato? I can't see!
Shinji: Hey, where am I supposed to go?
Shinji: Misato? Asuka? Ayanami? Toji? Kitsuke? Ritsuko? Kaji?
Shinji: Father!
Shinji: Mother...
Shinji: Somebody please tell me what I have to do now!
Shinji: Eva...
Shinji: Evangelion Unit 1...
Shinji: I still have to pilot it?
Shinji: Even after it made me kill him?
Shinji: My father and the others tell me that I have to pilot it no matter what I want!
Shinji: Why do I have to keep fighting after all that's happened?
Shinji: Mother! Say something!
Shinji: Answer me!
Shinji: Because everyone tells me to.
Shinji: What do you mean?
Shinji: It's for the sake of mankind.
Shinji: Isn't that good enough?
Shinji: That's right!
Shinji: Is there something wrong with that?
Shinji: I'm doing the right thing!
Shinji: And when I do it, the others appreciate me!
Shinji: The others like me then!
Asuka: You're lying!
Asuka: Are you stupid?
Asuka: You know damn well that you do this for yourself.
Asuka: You're just making up excuses like you always do.
Shinji: I do?
Asuka: Pretending you're sacrificing yourself is just another cop-out.
Asuka: It makes you feel so special to play the martyr.
Shinji: I'm not sure that's true.
Asuka: You're feeling lonely and isolated, nothing more.
Shinji: Am I?
Asuka: Of course you are!
Asuka: You live on sympathy and you get it with your Eva, Shinji!
Shinji: It could be true.
Asuka: You love having others depend upon you.
Asuka: It satisfies your twisted little mind.
Shinji: That could be...
Asuka: If you want real happiness, you've got to find it for yourself, not wait for someone to give it to you!
Rei: But isn't that what you've been doing?
Asuka: I didn't want to be in this thing again.
Asuka: They're forcing me to pilot this.
Asuka: But this piece of junk won't work.
Asuka: But it's only junk because of what I've become.
Asuka: I'm the garbage now.
Asuka: I'm worthless.
Asuka: Nobody needs me.
Asuka: But he needs a pilot who can't even control her own Eva.
Rei: You seek your own value in the perception of others.
Asuka: Shut up!
Rei: Do you fear being loved?
Rei: Do you fear being...
Rei: Are you afraid that you will lose your identity if others leave you?
Young Asuka: You pilot Eva so you'll be praised.
Asuka: Shut up! Shut up! Leave me alone!
Asuka: How can a wind-up doll like you dare tell me that?!
Rei: Who am I?
Rei: You are Rei Ayanami.
Rei: But who are you?
Rei: Are you Rei Ayanami as well?
Rei: Correct. I'm the thing that is recognized as Rei Ayanami.
Young Rei: We are all things that are recognized as Rei Ayanami.
Rei: How could all of those possibly be me?
Rei: It is simply because the others call us Rei Ayanami.
Rei: That is the only reason.
Young Rei: You possess a false body and a fake soul.
Young Rei: Do you know why?
Rei: I am neither false nor fake.
Rei: I am simply me.
Rei: No.
Rei: You are an empty shell with a false soul, created by a man named Gendo Ikari.
Rei: You are just an object that is pretending to be a human.
Rei: Look deep within yourself.
Rei: Do you perceive the almost intangible and invisible presence that lurks below your waking self?
Rei: Inside your darkest dreams, It is there that your true identity lies.
Rei: No, I am me.
Rei: I became myself by the instrumentality of the links and relationships between myself and others.
Rei: I am formed by interaction with others.
Rei: They create me as I create them.
Rei: These relationships and interactions serve to shape the patterns of my heart and mind.
Rei: Yes, that is the name for what I share with those who have created the thing known as Rei.
Rei: That is what will continue to shape me.
Young Rei: But there is someone else who is your true self.
Young Rei: You don't know her, but she exists.
Young Rei: You deny that fact in attempt to suppress that facet of your reality.
Young Rei: Because she might not have human form.
Young Rei: Because then the present self might cease to be.
Young Rei: This is what you fear, that you will become nothing.
Young Rei: You are frightened that you will disappear from the minds of others if another exists.
Rei: I'm afraid.
Rei: Why is that?
Rei: Because your current self will have never existed.
Rei: Because you will cease to be.
Rei: No, I'm not.
Rei: I am happy.
Rei: Because I want to die.
Rei: I want despair.
Rei: I want to return to nothing, but I can't.
Rei: He won't let me return to nothing.
Rei: There's nothing. There's nothing.
Rei: I still exist because he needs me.
Rei: But when everything is over, when I am of no use anymore, he will abandon me.
Rei: I've prayed for the day he would abandon me, but now, now I fear it.
Gendo: Come, let us go. This is the day for which you were created, Rei.
Rei: Yes, sir.
Shinji: What? What feeling is this? I think I've experienced this sensation before.
Shinji: It's as though my physical form was disappearing.
Shinji: It feels... agreeable.
Shinji: As though my existence is spreading itself out to cover the entirety of existence.
Gendo: Incorrect. It is not a return to nothingness.
Gendo: It is merely a return to a state of beginning.
Gendo: It is no less than a return to the primal womb that we lost so long ago.
Gendo: Souls and minds will become one, attaining eternal balance.
Gendo: The final goal is nothing more than that.
Misato: And that's instrumentality?
Ritsuko: Yes. There is an emptiness at the very core of our souls.
Ritsuko: A fundamental incompleteness that has haunted all beings since the very first thought.
Ritsuko: On a primal level, man has always been aware of the darkness that resides at the core of his mind.
Ritsuko: We have seeked to escape from this void and the fear it causes, and all man's accomplishments were made in the hope of filling it.
Misato: And so you'll just crush everyone's minds together to fill the gaps?
Misato: Who made you humanity's overseer?
Misato: You came to us bearing an offer of help, yet your benevolence has proved to be as false as our friendship!
Ritsuko: And yet that is exactly as you wished it to be!
Misato: Where am I?
Shinji: This is the me that exists in your mind, Misato.
Misato: And yet at the same time, this is also the me which exists in your mind, isn't it Shinji?
Shinji: In order to establish my identity, I have to communicate with the minds of many people.
Shinji: I have to examine that which is at my core.
Shinji: I have to stare at Misato, who resides on the inside of my mind.
Shinji: What is it that you wish for, Misato?
Young Misato: I have to be a good child.
Young Misato: Because I have no daddy.
Young Misato: Because I have to be good and not bother my mommy.
Young Misato: But I don't want to become like my mom.
Young Misato: When my father is not here, she always cries.
Young Misato: I can't cry. I can't depend on anyone else.
Young Misato: So I have to be good.
Young Misato: That way maybe my father won't hate me as much.
Young Misato: I hope. Maybe my father won't hate me if I be good.
Misato: But I hated my father.
Misato: And I hated being a good child.
Misato: I hate it.
Misato: I'm tired of it.
Misato: I'm tired of keeping myself clean.
Misato: I'm tired of pretending to be pure and noble.
Misato: I'm so tired of it all.
Misato: I want to disgrace myself to get so dirty that no one can stand it.
Misato: I'd want to see my life and my reputation ruined.
Ritsuko: Is that why you slept with him? With Kaji?
Misato: No! I slept with him because I love him!
Young Misato: You did? Did you really love him?
Misato: Yes, I did! He accepted me as myself, for the real me!
Misato: That's why I let him make love to me!
Maya: (dramatic music)
Misato: - No, don't show Shinji this.
Misato: I don't want him to see that side of me.
Kaji: - Why are you still embarrassed after all that's happened?
Misato: - Because I'm ashamed of it.
Misato: - Why does this embarrass you?
Misato: You weren't ashamed then.
Misato: You were glad to show your true nature to the man you loved.
Misato: In fact, you took great pleasure in it.
Misato: No, don't do this!
Misato: You wanted to dirty yourself?
Misato: You should be happy to show this side of yourself to Shinji, shouldn't you?
Misato: No! No, no!
Misato: Are you sure?
Misato: Or is it perhaps your father that you'd like to show this to?
Misato: No!
Misato: Wasn't it really peace of mind that you were seeking in Kaji's bed?
Misato: You wanted peace of mind and warmth from Kaji then?
Misato: No!
Misato: You wanted to find your father in Kaji's embrace, didn't you?
Rei: It's not true!
Misato: It is true. In Kaji, I'd found my father reborn.
Misato: And so I fled from him. I was so afraid.
Misato: He was so much like my father.
Misato: But at the same time, I was also very happy.
Misato: I was never happier.
Misato: That was such a wonderful time.
Misato: That's why I hated it.
Misato: That's why I left.
Misato: That's why I ran away.
Kaji: So, no reason was required to begin our love, but you needed a reason for ending it.
Misato: Yes, you were so kind, Kaji.
Misato: You were so kind to disgrace me, to dirty me, to deflower me.
Kaji: Just because you hate yourself is no reason to injure yourself further.
Kaji: Punishing yourself is simply a cheat to make you feel better for a little while.
Kaji: Don't do this to yourself.
Misato: Now you'll tell me to take care of myself?
Misato: Men always do that.
Misato: They'll escape to their jobs, their own world, and leave me behind.
Misato: They always leave me behind.
Young Misato: Always. Just like our father did.
Misato: They always escape from the harsh realities.
Misato: Harsh reality.
Misato: I am his harsh reality.
Misato: Of course, I am the problem.
Shinji: Stop this! Misato!
Misato: Why should anyone else love me anyway? I hate myself! [Maya] You're vulgar and impure. [Ritsuko] You're pathetic.
Asuka: You're gross and disgusting! I've never seen anyone in such a disgusting relationship!
Makoto: Congratulations on your promotion, Major Katsuragi.
Misato: The me who is recognized is the me who's performing a role in order to be appreciated.
Misato: But she's not the real me.
Young Misato: Your true self is always crying, isn't she?
Misato: Yes, but I am happy.
Misato: I am happy.
Misato: It's true, I am happy.
Misato: I'm not! This isn't the happiness I want!
Misato: This isn't me! It is not the true myself!
Misato: I just don't want to face the harsh reality!
Shinji: But we have to. We cannot live otherwise.
Shinji: You know you'd be alone and afraid.
Rei: Unstable.
Ritsuko: If nobody was sleeping next to you.
Asuka: Are you afraid of sleeping alone?
Maya: Or does sleeping by yourself remind you of how empty your life is?
Kaji: She can't stand not having other souls around her.
Makoto: So, you'll sleep with anyone, won't you, Major?
Misato: No!
Misato: Yes, you just want to be infatuated with primal ecstasy.
Misato: You want to fill the hole in your heart with temporary escape.
Misato: You take advantage of men to soothe the pain in your soul.
Misato: No! No! No!
Asuka: Where am I?
Shinji: This is the me which exists in your mind, Asuka.
Asuka: And also, this is the me that exists in Shinji's mind at the same time.
Shinji: What do you want, Asuka?
Young Asuka: I want to live by myself!
Young Asuka: I don't want my papa and my mama!
Young Asuka: I'll live by myself!
Young Asuka: And then, I won't cry anymore!
Asuka: But I'm still crying!
Asuka: Why am I crying?
Asuka's Step Mom: I am sorry, I just don't like her.
Mr. Langley: What happened to you, the able doctor?
Rei: I told you, I'm a human being before a doctor
Mr. Langley: But how can a trained person like you...
Asuka's Step Mom: She acts too much like an adult, and she rejects me absolutely.
Asuka's Step Mom: Sometimes she even scares me.
Asuka's Step Mom: Have you had such a feeling with her?
Mr. Langley: No, and in any case, you have now become Asuka's mother.
Asuka's Step Mom: I'm your wife before that.
Mr. Langley: Both duties are concurrent.
Asuka's Step Mom: In a social perspective, yes.
Asuka's Step Mom: But you can't quit being her father.
Asuka's Step Mom: However, I can quit being her mother anytime.
Mr. Langley: Hmph. You can say that.
Young Asuka: No, Mama! Don't leave me!
Young Asuka: I'll be good, promise!
Young Asuka: Don't stop being my mother!
Young Asuka: Don't ignore me!
Young Asuka: No, Mama!
Young Asuka: Don't kill me!
Kyoko: Your papa hates your mama.
Kyoko: He doesn't need me anymore.
Kyoko: No.
Kyoko: He didn't love me to begin with.
Kyoko: But let's die together.
Kyoko: Because he doesn't want us.
Kyoko: He didn't need me at all.
Kyoko: And he doesn't want you either, Husk.
Young Asuka: I'm not wanted?
Asuka: I'm not worth anything?
Kyoko: Die with me, die with me.
Young Asuka: No! I am not your doll!
Young Asuka: I'll think by myself and live by myself!
Asuka: And then, my mother was hanging from the ceiling.
Asuka: She looked so happy.
Asuka: But I hated how she looked.
Asuka: I don't want to die.
Asuka: I don't want to disappear.
Asuka: I hate this!
Asuka: I hate boys!
Asuka: I hate my father and my mother. I hate everyone.
Asuka: Nobody cares about me. Nobody stays with me.
Asuka: So I don't want to depend on anybody.
Asuka: But I hate it at the same time. It's a pain.
Asuka: I don't want to be alone. I don't want to be alone.
Asuka: I don't want to be alone.
Shinji: Don't leave me. [Misato] Don't ignore me.
Asuka: Don't kill me!
Shinji: What the hell is this?
Misato: This is the instrumentality which your father has initiated.
Shinji: This is it?
Misato: This is part of it.
Asuka: You can't tell what the truth is, Shinji.
Ritsuko: Truth is subjective. Therefore, you can barely tell that what you can feel is fact.
Rei: The truth is within you.
Fuyutsuki: And the facts that remain in your memory are what will become your truth.
Ritsuko: Truth can be changed from time to time. Sometimes.
Shinji: This is all fact. This is the result of everything?
Asuka: This is real, but one of many realities.
Misato: This is the conclusion you wanted.
Shinji: Wanted? Me?
Rei: Yes. Total destruction.
Rei: You wished for a world in which nobody would be saved.
Shinji: No! I didn't wish for this! The others didn't save me!
Ritsuko: Nobody can save you from yourself.
Kaji: This is what you wished for.
Asuka: Destruction, death, and return to nothingness.
Asuka: You wished for these.
Misato: This is the reality that is.
Shinji: What is reality?
Rei: This is your world.
Makoto: A world that exists solely for yourself.
Makoto: One without time, space, or anyone else.
Shigeru: A world in which every facet is determined by you.
Maya: This is the world in which you just wait for others to give you something.
Misato: This is your world unless you decide to change reality.
Shinji: This is the world that is! Nothing can change that!
Ritsuko: No. You yourself make the decision.
Fuyutsuki: This is the world where your mind decides what will be.
Misato: Whether it is the will to survive, [Asuka] or a wish for death, it is all up to you.
Shinji: Are you saying that this darkness, this insane world, are what I really wish to create?
Asuka: Yes.
Kaji: You wished for a closed world that was comfortable for you.
Makoto: You wished for it in order to protect you from your weakness.
Shigeru: To protect your few pleasures.
Rei: This is merely the result of your wish.
Misato: In your closed world, in a world where only you are allowed to be, others cannot live with you.
Asuka: But still you wished to close off the world that surrounded you.
Ritsuko: Your wish ejected things you disliked and created an isolated and lonely world filled with nothing.
Rei: This is the world your wishes have created.
Rei: A private haven in the recesses of your mind.
Asuka: This is how it all ends one of many possible endings. [Misato]This is an ending you brought upon yourself. You choose this fate
Misato: An end always comes after a beginning.
Misato: Will our hopes result in ultimate destruction?
Misato: Is our whole existence death itself?
Misato: It's our final episode, "The Beast That Shouted 'Ai' in the Heart of the World!"
Misato: [music ends]