Yoko Takahashi (GeekyFanDubs):
Like an angel,
who has forsaken sympathy,
Planning & Original Story
GAINAX
rise up young boy and
make yourself a legend!
Planning
PROJECT EVA.
Manga published in
SHONEN ACE
from
KADOKAWA SHOTEN
PUBLISHING CO., LTD.
エヴァンゲリオン
Evangerion (Japanese pronunciation)
Official English: Evangelion
新世紀
Shin Seiki
Literal: New Century
Blue skies, and beckoning winds,
are trying to open the door of your heart.
Character Designs
YOSHIYUKI SADAMOTO
Mecha Design
IKUTO YAMASHITA
HIDEAKI ANNO
Assistant Director
MASAYUKI
KAZUYA TSURUMAKI
But you're gazing at me, as if you cannot see.
You just stand there smiling vacantly.
Art Director
HIROSHI KATO
Coloring Design
HARUMI TAKAHOSHI
Director of Photography
YOICHI KURODA
Sound Director
HIDEYUKI TANAKA
Sound Production
AUDIO TANAKA
Your eyes, hold such innocence.
You're blind to the fate that will soon come to pass.
Music
SHIROH SAGISU
Music Cooperation
TV Tokyo Music
But it's summoning you, with a touch like a sigh.
You seek it without knowing why.
Opening Theme
"A Cruel Angel's Thesis"
残酷な天使のテーゼ
Zankoku na Tenshi no Tēze
Literal: The Thesis of a Cruel Angel
Lyrics: Neko Oikawa
Composition: Hidetoshi Sato
Arrangement: Toshiyuki Ohmori
Performed by: Yoko Takahashi
(Star Child Records)
Closing Theme
But someday I know that you will be awakened
and your eyes will finally see,
Opening Animation
Animation
YUTAKA HONDA
SHINYA HASEGAWA
Episode Direction
KAZUYA TSURUMAKI
These wings on your back are just waiting to guide you.
The future will soon set you free!
Public Relations
REI ANAMI (TV Tokyo)
HIROKI SATO (GAINAX)
Animation Production
TATSUNOKO PRO
GAINAX
Producer
NORIKO KOBAYASHI
(TV TOKYO)
YUTAKA SUGIYAMA
This cruel thesis, a spiteful angel's litany,
will soon soar from the window of your destiny.
TOP SECRET
Human Instrumentality Project
United Nations Executive Council
17th Interim Report
Human Instrumentality Committee
FY2015 Operations Plan Summary
Summary Edition
SAMPLE A-01 ADAM
Who is Adam? He is living. Why?
Caution.....+42.....
White hot pathos, a desecrated symphony,
Stay true to this and don't betray your mem'ry!
Come now, reach out. You must embrace reality.
Rise up, young boy, and make yourself a legend!
Director
Hideaki Anno
Production
TV TOKYO
NAS
The year is 2015 A.D.
[Cicadas droning]
May I have your attention.
As of 12.30 p.m. today, a special state of emergency has been declared for the Kanto and Chubu region surrounding the Tokai district.
All residents must evacuate to their designated shelters immediately.
来々軒 Rairaiken (a restaurant)
Repeat. As of 12.30 p.m. today, a state of emergency has been declared for the Kanto and Chubu regions surrounding the Tokai district.
All Lines Stopped
All residents must evacuate to their shelters immediately.
Misato: Damn! Why did I have to lose him at a time like this? Why now? (Sigh)
lkari Shinji
We're sorry. Due to the state of special emergency, no lines are currently available. This is a recording.
Shinji: Ugh. It's no use. This is dumb! I shouldn't have come here. Ahh!
To Shinji
I'll be coming
to get you,
so wait for me.
Attention
here
please!
To Shinji
I'll be coming
to get you,
so wait for me.
Attention
here
please!
Shinji: I guess we won't be meeting here.
Shinji: Maybe I should, find a shelter.
Shinji: Huh?
Shinji: Woah!
友銀行 Friend Bank     早雲山運送 Sōunzan Transport
Shinji: Hhh. Ahh. Ohh. Huh?
Shinji: Ohh.
Estimated Path
Female Voice: Unidentified intruder is still coming towards us.
Male Voice: We've got it on visual. I'm putting it on the main screen.
Fuyutsuki: It's been 15 years.
Gendo: Yes. Well now we know for sure.
Gendo: The angels are back.
episode one
Angel
Attack
Shinji: Ah! Ahh!
Male Voice: Every single missile hit the target!
Male Voice: No! Ahh!
Shinji: Ah! Oh. Uh. Uh!
Shinji: Ahh! Oh. Hh. Hh.
Shinji: Uh. Ahh! Oh.
Shinji: Uh. Uh.
Misato: Sorry! Get in! Am I real late?
Shinji: Eh. Oh. Ah! Hh. Ohh! Oh. Ahh!
Male Voice: The target's still coming towards us. It's headed straight for Tokyo 3.
Female Voice: The air defense force doesn't have enough firepower to stop it!
Generals: Fire everything we've got! Mobilize the Atsugi and Iruma Forces!
Generals: Don't hold anything back! Destroy that thing at any cost!
Generals: It's not possible! That was a direct hit!
Generals: The tank battalion's been wiped out! Guided missiles and artillery fire seem to have no effect at all!
Generals: Damn it! We've hit it with everything we've got and we're not even touching it!
Fuyutsuki: Looks like an AT field. Hmm?
Gendo: Yes. Conventional weapons are no match for the Angels.
Generals: I understand, sir. We'll execute backup plan at once.
Misato: Now wait a second!
Misato: No! They're gonna use an N2 mine!
Misato: Get down!
Shinji: (Muffled).
Both: Ooh. Ow! Oh!
Both: Oh! Ow!
Both: Ohhh.
Generals: Yeah! We did it! Alright!
Generals: Well, Ikari, it looks like you won't be getting a shot at it.
Female Voice: Shockwave approaching.
Shinji: Coughs
Misato: Are you all right?
Shinji: Yeah.
Shinji: But my mouth is full of dirt. Puh.
Misato: You'll be all right. Come on.
Misato: Ready to push?
Misato: Go!
Misato: Push!
Shinji: Err!
Misato: Giyah!
Misato: Yeah!
Misato: Hah! Thanks, Shinji. You're pretty useful.
Shinji: Thank you, but I should thank you, Miss Katsuragi.
Misato: Uh, Misato is fine.
Misato: So, Shinji Ikari, we meet at last.
Misato: Uh, yeah.
Generals: What's the status of the target?
Female Voice: We're unable to confirm. The EM-pulse knocked everything out.
Generals: It must be dead. It took the full blast.
Male Voice: External sensors restored.
Female Voice: Energy rating at the epicenter!
Generals: It can't be!
Male Voice: External cameras online.
Generals: What the-
Generals: That was our last resort.
Generals: No effect at all.
Generals: It's a demon!
Misato: Yes, don't worry.
Misato: His safety is my top priority.
Misato: Look, can you get a car train ready for us?
Misato: An express, of course.
Misato: Well, I did volunteer to pick him up, so it's only my duty to make sure he gets there.
Misato: See ya.
Misato: (V.O.) Oh, this stinks. I just had this car repaired and it's a total wreck already.
Misato: 33 more payments to go, plus the cost of repairs.
Misato: And look, my favorite dress is ruined. Ruined!
Shinji: Um, Miss Misato?
Misato: (V.O.) And I look so good in it.
Shinji: Excuse me, Misato.
Misato: Hmm? What's that?
Shinji: Those batteries, isn't that, um, theft?
Misato: Uh, don't worry about it.
Misato: Uh, it's an emergency and we needed a working car, right? Heh!
Misato: Uh, I am a government official after all, so, everything's gonna be perfectly fine, okay?
Misato: Okay.
Shinji: Mm. I don't think anyone will buy that excuse.
Misato: You're no fun.
Misato: You know, you're not as cute as I thought you were.
Shinji: Hmph. Is that so?
Misato: Ooh, angry?
Misato: I'm sorry.
Misato: Hahaha. You're just a boy after all.
Shinji: You're not as mature as I thought you'd be either.
(Oorh!) (Aah! Hey watch out! Woah!)
Generals: As we suspected, it's regenerating itself.
Gendo: Without that ability, it couldn't operate without support units.
Fuyutsuki: Well, quite impressive.
Fuyutsuki: It can upgrade its operational parameters.
Gendo: And it's also getting smarter.
Fuyutsuki: It should renew its attack any minute now.
Female Voice: The gates are now closing. Please stand clear.
Female Voice: This is a B-22 special express departing from G-33-1. This train will bypass all other stations. Please stand back
Shinji: NERV?
Misato:Ah-huh! It's a secret organization controlled by the UN.
Shinji: And that's where my father works?
Misato: Well, yeah! You do know what he does, don't you?
Shinji: (Sigh) All my teachers told me, was, that it was important to the future of, mankind.
Generals: Command of this operation is being entrusted to you. Don't betray our trust.
Gendo: Yes, sir.
Generals: Mr. Ikari, we've already seen that our weapons seem to have no effect on these things.
Generals: That's why we're giving you a chance.
Generals: Are you sure that you can beat them?
Gendo: That is why NERV exists.
Generals: I pray you're right.
Ibuki: The target is still stationary.
Makoto: Estimated current ability to intercept is only 7.5%.
Fuyutsuki: The UN forces are exhausted. What are you going to do?
Gendo: Activate Unit-01.
Fuyutsuki: Activate it? But we have no pilot.
Gendo: Not anymore. Another spare is being delivered.
Shinji: Misato, are we going to see my father?
Misato: (Sigh) Of course. Of course we are.
Shinji: Mmm. Father. (Train sounds)
Misato: Oh, yeah.
Misato: Did your dad send you an ID card?
Shinji: Huh? Umm. Yeah.
Shinji: This is it.
Misato: Oh, thanks.
Come.
Ikari
Gendo
Misato: Here, start reading this, okay?
Welcome to
Shinji: NERV.
Shinji: My father's agency.
Shinji: Am I gonna be working for him?
Misato: Mm.
Shinji: What am I saying?
Shinji: He wouldn't have sent me a letter unless he needed me for something.
Misato: Hmm. Sounds like you don't get along with your dad.
Misato: Huh, you sound just like me.
Shinji: Woah! Oh! Awesome!
Shinji: Oh! It's a real GeoFront!
Misato: That's right.
Misato: This is our secret underground base.
Misato: NERV Central.
Misato: This city is the key to rebuilding our world.
Misato: A fortress for all mankind.
エヴァンゲリオン
Evangerion (Japanese pronunciation)
Official English: Evangelion
新世紀
Shin Seiki
Literal: New Century
Misato: (Sigh) What on Earth? Isn't this the right way?
Nerv Headquarters
Around here
Female Voice: Central Dogma's closed passages remain sealed. Opening lock B-26 in sequence.
Misato: It's because of these things that I hate to wear a skirt around here.
Shinji: Mm-hm.
Misato: I wonder where in the heck Ritsuko is.
Misato: I'm sorry. I'm not used to this place.
Shinji: We passed this spot twice already.
Misato: Rrr. Well don't worry about it! They make those transit things to be used you know!
Female Voice: Would the chairperson of E Project, Technical Division 1, Dr Ritsuko Akagi, please contact, Captain Misato Katsuragi, of Operations Division 1, immediately.
Air
Ritsuko: I don't believe it. Is she lost again?
ここは  です This is
Misato: Uh, hi there, Ritsuko.
Ritsuko: Hmm.
Misato: Uh, ugh.
Ritsuko: Why are you wasting my time, *Captain*?
Ritsuko: Don't you know we're short on time *and* manpower?
Misato: Eheh, Sorry.
Ritsuko: So, is this the boy?
Misato: Uhh, right. According to the Marduk report, he's the third child.
Ritsuko: Hmm. Pleased to meet you.
Misato: Hm? Oh! Sure.
Misato: I'm afraid he's just like his father.
Misato: The gruff and unfriendly part, that is. (Hm)
Gendo: Handle the rest of this.
Fuyutsuki: Their first meeting in three years.
Makoto: Sir?
Fuyutsuki: Mm?
Makoto: It looks like the target's starting to move again.
Fuyutsuki: I see. Let's go to battle stations. Level 1.
Female Voice: Battle stations. Level 1. Prepare for ground level intercept.
Misato: There we go.
Ritsuko: It sounds pretty serious.
Misato: So how's Unit-01 coming?
Ritsuko: It's currently undergoing refrigeration using the B-type equipment.
Misato: Does it really work? It's never worked before, has it?
Ritsuko: The possibility of activation is 0.00000, 00001%.
Ritsuko: Around here we just call it the 09 system.
Misato: Does that mean it doesn't work?
Ritsuko: Don't be insulting. It's 09 as in Oni, a Japanese devil.
Shinji: Huh.
Misato: Well, anyway! I suppose it's a bit late to be saying, "Sorry it doesn't work."
左 Left
Shinji: Hey! Uh. Eh. Why is it so dark in here?
Shinji: Wuh? Agh! Uh. Ooh.
Shinji: Oh! It's a face! A giant robot! Oh.
Ritsuko: You won't find this in there.
Shinji: What?
Ritsuko: This is man's ultimate fighting machine.
Ritsuko: The synthetic life form known as Evangelion.
Ritsuko: Unit-01.
Ritsuko: Built here in secret.
Ritsuko: It is mankind's last hope.
Shinji: Is this my father's work?
Gendo: Correct.
Shinji: Oh!
Gendo: It's been a while.
Shinji: Father...
Gendo: Hph. We're moving out.
Misato: Moving out? But Unit-00's still in cryostasis! Huh?
Misato: Wait a minute! You're gonna use Unit-01?
Ritsuko: There's no other way.
Misato: Now wait! Rei can't do it yet, can she?
Misato: We don't have a pilot!
Ritsuko: We just received one.
Misato: You're serious?
Ritsuko: Shinji Ikari?
Shinji: Huh?
Ritsuko: You will pilot it.
Misato: But even Rei Ayanami took seven months to synchronize with her EVA.
Misato: It's impossible for him to do it.
Misato: He *just* *got* here!
Ritsuko: He just has to sit in the seat.
Ritsuko: We don't expect more than that.
Misato: Uhh but...
Ritsuko: Listen, defeating that angel is our ultimate priority.
Ritsuko: If we have someone who has a chance at synchronizing with an EVA,
Ritsuko: then we've got to risk it.
Ritsuko: You do understand that, don't you, *Captain* Katsuragi?
Misato: Yes, ma'am.
Shinji: Why did, you send for me?
Gendo: You know why I sent for you.
Shinji: So, you're asking me to take this thing, and go out there and fight?
Gendo: Correct.
Shinji: How could you do this to me? I thought you didn't want me.
Shinji: Why? Why did you have to call me now, Father?
Gendo: Because I have a use for you.
Shinji: (Video) But why? Why me?
Gendo: Because there is no one else who can.
Shinji: No, I can't! I've never even seen anything like this before!
Shinji: There's no way I can do this!
Gendo: You will be instructed.
Shinji: But still! There's no way! I can't pilot that thing!
Gendo: If you're going to do it, do it now. If not, then leave.
Gendo: It's close. It must sense us.
Ritsuko: Shinji, we don't have much time.
Shinji: Uh?
Misato: Get inside.
Shinji: This is all wrong. I came all this way.
Shinji: Awh, why did I come?
Misato: Why, Shinji? Exactly why did you come here?
Shinji: Uh, eh.
Misato: You mustn't run away. You must confront your father, and you must confront yourself.
Shinji: Rrr, I know that! But I just can't!
Gendo: Fuyutsuki!
Fuyutsuki: (Video) Sir!
Gendo: Wake up Rei.
Fuyutsuki: Can we use her?
Gendo: She's not dead yet.
Fuyutsuki: Understood.
Gendo: Rei?
Rei: (Whispers) Yes?
Gendo: Our spare is unusable. You will do it again.
Rei: Yes, sir.
Ritsuko: Reconfigure Unit-01 system for Rei, then activate.
Ibuki: Roger. Calling off current program, and beginning activation.
Shinji: I knew it! Huh. I'm not needed after all. Mm.
Shinji: Oh...
Rei: Ahh. Hf. Ohh. Hu. Hm.
Rei: Aah!
Shinji: Woah. Owh!
Misato: Look out!
Shinji: Ahhh!
Shinji: Oh?
Gendo: Hm!
Makoto: The EVA activated itself!
Makoto: It ripped right out of the right arm restraint!
Ritsuko: No! That's not possible!
Ritsuko: The entry plug wasn't even inserted!
Ritsuko: That just can't happen!
Misato: Hah, you mean it reacted without any kind of interface?
Misato: Was it really to protect something? To protect him?
Misato: Hah. It's him!
Rei: Heh. Ah! Hf.
Shinji: Uh. Oh.
Rei: Eeh! Aah! Ehuh.
Shiji: Huh? Ohh. Mmm.
Shinji: I mustn't run away. I mustn't run away. I mustn't run away. I mustn't run away. I mustn't *run away*!
Shinji: I'll do it! I'll pilot it!
Male Voice: (Radio) Cooling process completed.
Left
Male Voice: Right arm repairs completed.
Male Voice: Cage now in position for docking.
Ibuki: Signal plug terminator now being ejected.
Male Voice: (Radio) Roger. Insert an entry plug.
Male Voice: Plug locked in place.
Male Voice: Connecting UNIT-01.
Shinji: Mmm.
Shinji: Hm?
Shinji: Uh, what is this stuff?
Shinji: Ooh. Wao-! (Muffled) Mm! Mm!
Ritsuko: Don't worry.
Ritsuko: Once your lungs are filled with LCL,
Ritsuko: your blood will be oxygenated directly.
Ritsuko: (Radio) It's okay. You'll get used to it.
Shinji: (Garbled) I'm gonna be sick.
Misato: Stop complaining. You're a boy, you know.
高圧電流 High Voltage
Male Voice: (Radio) Connecting main power.
Male Voice: All circuits transmitting.
Female Voice: (Radio) Roger.
Ibuki: (Radio) Connecting secondary contacts.
Wah?
Ibuki: A-10 NERV connection normal.
Ritsuko: Configure the language logic interface for Japanese.
Ibuki: All preliminary contacts established. Performance nominal.
Woah.
Ibuki: Bi-directional circuits are open.
Ibuki: Synchronization ratio at 41.3%.
Ritsuko: Amazing!
Ibuki: Harmonics seem to be normal.
Ibuki: I see no disturbances.
Ritsuko: Let's do it!
Misato: Mmm! Begin launch sequence!
Male Voice: Beginning launch sequence!
Male Voice: Removing primary lock bolts!
Male Voice: Removal confirmed.
Male Voice: Removing the umbilical bridge.
Male Voice: Removing secondary lock bolts!
安全 + 第一 Safety First
Male Voice: Removing primary restraints.
Male Voice: Removing secondary restraints.
Male Voice: Releasing safety locks number 1 through 15!
Male Voice: Internal batteries fully charged!
Male Voice: External battery outlet closed!
Ibuki: Roger. Move EVA Unit-01 to the launch pad.
危険 Danger     保ゴ めがね Wear safety glasses
Ibuki: Launch path clear. All systems green.
Ritsuko: Evangelion, ready for launch!
Misato: Understood! Can we really do this?
Gendo: Of course. Unless we defeat the Angels, we have no future.
Fuyutsuki: Ikari, are you absolutely certain?
Gendo: Heh.
Misato: EVA launch!
危険 Danger
保ゴ めがね
Wear safety glasses
Shinji: Ahhh!
Shinji: Woah! Huh. Uh.
Misato: Shinji, don't get killed out there.
To Be
Continued
Claire Littley: Fly me to the moon,
Script
HIDEAKI ANNO
Storyboard
YUKI MASAMI
HIDEAKI ANNO
Episode Director
KAZUYA TSURUMAKI
And let me play among the stars.
CAST
SHINJI IKARI
MEGUMI OGATA
MISATO KATSURAGI
KOTONO MITSUISHI
RITSUKO AKAGI
YURIKO YAMAGUCHI
REI AYANAMI
MEGUMI HAYASHIBARA
Let me see what spring is like on Jupiter and Mars.
CAST
GENDO IKARI
FUMIHIKO TACHIKI
KOZO FUYUTSUKI
MOTOMU KIYOKAWA
MAKOTO HYUGA
YUU ASAKAWA
MAYA IBUKI
MIKI NAGASAWA
CAST
SHIGERU AOBA
TAKEHITO KOYASU
MILITARY PERSONNEL
TOMOMICHI NISHIMURA
HIDENARI UGAKI
HIROSHI NAKA
AKIKO HIRAMATSU
TAKASHI NAGASAKO
In other words, hold my hand!
Animation Director
SHUNJI SUZUKI
Setting Assistance
YOSHITOO ASARI
SEIJI KIO
ISAMU IMAGAKE
Ending Animation
YUKI MASAMI
Key Animation
MITSUO ISO
KATSUICHI NAKAYAMA
SHINYA TAKAHASHI
HIROKI TAKAGI
YUTAKA HONDA
KAZUYA KURODA
In other words, darling, kiss me.
Key Animation
NAOYA FURUKAWA
HIDEYUKI MORIOKA
HIDENORI FUKUOKA
SHIGEKI SUNADA
AKIRA YOSHINARI
ISAMU IMAGAKE
Animation Check
YASUHITO MURATA
Animation
TAKAHIRO ONODA
SEIICHIRO SHINOKURA
STUDIO ALGO SHIP
STUDIO JUNGLE GYM
MARSA CO., LTD.
STUDIO DEEN
Fill my heart with song,
Color Design & Inspection
HARUMI TAKABOSHI
Special Effects
NORIYUKI OHTA
CG Production
GAINAX SHOP
and let me sing forever more.
Finishing
TATSUNOKO COLOR CENTER
HIDEKO KITAZUME
KIYOKO MOMOSE
CHIEKO ODAKA
MARSA CO., LTD.
RISU WORK
MAKI PRO
and let me sing forever more.
You are all I long for, all I worship and adore.
Background Art
STUDIO BIHOU
HIROSHI KATO
TATSUYA KUSHIDA
YUSUKE TAKEDA
DAI OHTA
MASARU SATO
TATSURO ISERI
Photography
COSMOS
MOTOAKI IKEGAMI
NORIKO SUZUKI
HIROSHI NOGUCHI
NAOHISA HAISHIMA
YUUICHI ONO
JUNICHI YAITABASHI
KOUICHI FURUSAWA
In other words, please be true!
Editing
SACHI MIKI
Film Processing
TOKYO LABORATORY
Production Desk
HIROMICHI OISHI
Production Manager
KEN ANDO
Producer's Assistant
TOMOKO TAKAHASHI
Sound Effects
TORU NOGUCHI
(Anime Sound)
Audio Mixing
YOSHIO OBARA
STUDIO
TAVAC
Video Editing
HIROSHI UCHIMURA
(TRYGON)
Operator
KOZO YONEYAMA
(VIDEO SUNMALL)
In other words, I love you!
Animation Producers
MOTOKI UEDA
SHUJI UCHIYAMA
HIROYUKI YAMAGA
Production
TV TOKYO
Chu!
NAS
Preview
Misato: The Eva triumphs, but this angel is only the beginning.
Misato: Worried about Shinji's mental state, Misato brashly decides to move him in with her.
Misato: However, Shinji's mind only becomes more shut off from the rest of the world.
Misato: It all happens in the next episode, and I'll be slipping you a little *extra* as well.
Next Time
Unfamiliar Ceiling
ENGLISH VOCAL CAST
Shinji Ikari: Spike Spencer
Misato Katsuragi: Allison Keith
Ritsuko Akagi: Sue Ulu
Rei Ayanami: Amanda Winn
Gendo Ikari: Tristan MacAvery
Kouzou Fuyutsuki: Guil Lunde
Maya Ibuki: Kendra Benham
Makoto Hyuga: Brian Granveldt
Shigeru Aoba: Jason Lee
A.D.V. FILMS ENGLISH VERSION — Executive Producers: John Ledford, Mark Williams • Produced & Written by: Matt Greenfield • International Coordinator: Toru Iwakami • Project Translator: Kuni Kimura • Additional Translation: Shoko Oono • Directors: Matt Greenfield, Amanda Winn • Subtitle Script & Timing: Andrew Kent • Recorded at: Industrial Smoke & Mirrors • ADR Engineer: Charles Campbell • 5.1 Sound Design & Mix: Wade Shemwell • ADR Editors: Matt Crawford, Jason Grundy, Jacob A. Gragard, Wade Shemwell, Jon Duckworth • Post Production Manager: Shelly Thomas • Post Production: Monkey Boy Post • Editors: Joey Goubeaud, Neil O'Sullivan • Creative Directors: Chris Hawley, David Del Rio • Production Assistants: Maria Bechtol, Carole Pavlik, Robert Marchand